{
  "reference_number": "11137",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a 2050 target in legislation now",
      "answer_index": 0,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "The legislation should establish the goal of limiting warming to 1.5 degrees. We should not settle for 2 degrees warming, that would\n\n lock in devastating impacts on Pacific Island states and cause significant extinctions. That is not acceptable. To give us the best\n possibility of achieving no more than 1.5 degrees warming by the end of the century, there must be rapid cuts in all greenhouse\n\n gases beginning now. I support a net-zero target of 2040 with the majority of cuts occurring over the next decade. I support all\n greenhouse gases being included in the law, consistent with international climate frameworks. The Intergovernmental Panel on\n Climate Change makes it clear that methane reduction is critical to success in tackling climate change. It is politically and scientifically\n\n untenable for New Zealand’s climate law to exclude any gases from our biggest emitting sector - the agricultural sector. We also need\n gross emissions reduction targets. While I support the reforestation of large areas (particularly with native trees), we need to avoid\n\n over-reliance on forests as carbon sinks in our carbon accounting. As the Parliamentary Commissioner for the Environment has\n stated, “Each tonne of emissions offset by forestry is a tonne not reduced at source. Relying too heavily on forestry could lead to\n continued high levels of gross emissions.\" A target should also be set to achieve net negative emissions, or \"drawdown\", equivalent\n\n to emissions being 120% below 1990 levels by 2050. Finally, New Zealand should also strengthen it's Paris Agreement commitment,\n in line with achieving net zero carbon dioxide by 2040."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "I support the ‘firewall’ principle, that New Zealand’s targets must be achieved by actual cuts in our own emissions, and not through\n the purchase of overseas carbon credits or an over-reliance on forests as carbon sinks."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "I am cautious about how answers to this question will be aggregated and interpreted, and have therefore answered 'No' to this\n question. Targets should not be allowed to be weakened, only strengthened."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes. There should also be a requirement that the largest cuts occur in the first decade following implementation of the Act, with this\n\n being reflected in the budgets."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "I am cautious about how answers to this question will be aggregated and interpreted, and have therefore answered 'No' to this\nquestion. Targets should not be allowed to be weakened, only strengthened."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes, together with the following: to reduce cumulative emissions sufficiently to avoid dangerous climate change, the steepest\nemissions cuts to carbon dioxide must occur in the first 10 years."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes. We must learn from the mistakes of the UK's Climate Change Act and specify a strict time frame (6 months) for producing a plan."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The Government’s policy plans to meet emission budgets should be comprehensive, fair, cost-effective, environmentally sustainable,\nand reflect a commitment to Te Tiriti o Waitangi. The impact on vulnerable people should particularly be considered. Beneficiary\n\ngroups, unions, and iwi need to be worked with."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "Yes. The Commission should not be a decision-making body. However, the Government should be legally required to consider and\nformally respond to the Commission’s advice, and to provide an explanation if they do not act on it."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "I believe the ETS should be replaced with a carbon charge."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "The Government should prepare a National Climate Risk Assessment and an Adaptation Programme to address the climate risks\nidentified in this Assessment."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": null
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The world needs pathways to transformational change if we are to avoid catastrophic warming. This is the scale of the challenge. The\nscience is clear: the only way we can succeed is with big ambition. New Zealand must be bold and pass strong law for the sake of our\n\nprecious earth and future generations."
    }
  ]
}
